<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>FreeCAD Development Blog (Posts about bcf)</title><link>https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog/categories/bcf.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:info@freecadweb.org"&gt;FreeCAD Community&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 May 2019 17:46:20 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Advancing to the Viewpoint.bcf part</title><link>https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog/posts/finishing-up-the-datamodel-uml/</link><dc:creator>FreeCAD Community</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://forum.freecadweb.org/viewtopic.php?p=308095#p308095"&gt;forum post&lt;/a&gt; yesterday, Yorik pointed out that, although part of the
specification, the BimSnippet does not have to be treated with high priority. He
also referred me to Bernd and Duncan in case of questions arising.
As advised, I will consider the BimSnippet in the data model but probably won't
implement it right away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The progress I made today was mostly in understanding the BCF specification in
regards to the viewpoint.bcfv file. Multiple viewpoint files can be contained
within the folder of one topic. At the beginning of the day I thought that the
data model would be finished rather quick but as it turned out the documentation
on it is not as concise as one might wish it to be. To be more precise: the
whole section about the "Components" element is a bit confusing. It lists
multiple "properties", like &lt;cite&gt;Selection&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Visibility&lt;/cite&gt;. My intuition says that
&lt;cite&gt;Selection&lt;/cite&gt; contains a list of components that are selected, and &lt;cite&gt;Visibility&lt;/cite&gt;
specifies whether these components shall be visible or not. But in reality each
contains a list of components onto which the values of the attributes of the
respective property shall be applied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a bit confusing at first, and still is for me. Because of this ambiguity
I decided, for the further data model design, that refer to the related XML
schemas rather than the written documentation. For example here you can find the
schema for the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/buildingSMART/BCF-XML/blob/master/Schemas/visinfo.xsd"&gt;viewpoint.bcf&lt;/a&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But since the last time I have worked with XML schemas was in vocational school
(I think 2012) I have to refresh my memory on it. For that I will go through the
relevant parts of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.w3schools.com/xml/schema_intro.asp"&gt;W3CSchools: XML Schema Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;. Tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bcf</category><category>bim</category><category>class-diagram</category><category>GSoC</category><guid>https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog/posts/finishing-up-the-datamodel-uml/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2019 03:42:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Representing markup.bcf in UML</title><link>https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog/posts/representing-markupbcf-in-uml/</link><dc:creator>FreeCAD Community</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I mostly finished the UML class diagram in regard to representing the data
of the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;markup.bcf&lt;/tt&gt; file. One think I found kind of interesing while creating
the diagram is that in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/BuildingSMART/BCF-XML/tree/master/Documentation"&gt;BCF-XML-Documentation&lt;/a&gt; There is no link between a
topic and a comment, so no id of one is stored in the other. That didn't make
sense at first because I thought that one &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;markup&lt;/tt&gt; could have multiple topics,
which is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However one think what is not that obvious to me is the case with the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;BIMSnippet&lt;/tt&gt;.
On the documentation page it says that: "BimSnippet is an additional file containing
information related to one or multiple topics.". This would imply that there
would be more topics inside one &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;markup.bcf&lt;/tt&gt; file, because &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;BimSnippet&lt;/tt&gt; is,
as I understand, also just a node inside &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;markup.bcf&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding the open question from the previous post: How to represent constraints
defined in &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;extensions.xsd&lt;/tt&gt;; I thought about it a little today and came to the
conclusion that it would be the best approach to go with the last option I
listed. That means that for every node, for which constraints are listed in
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;extensions.xsd&lt;/tt&gt;, an empty enumeration/class is created which then, during
runtime, gets populated with the valid values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPDATE (2019-05-13): The inconsistency is resolved. The BimSnippet node just references one
file that does not have to be inside the topic folder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bcf</category><category>bim</category><category>class-diagram</category><category>GSoC</category><guid>https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog/posts/representing-markupbcf-in-uml/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2019 17:43:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>How to represent extension.xsd constraints</title><link>https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog/posts/how-to-represent-extensionxsd-constraints/</link><dc:creator>FreeCAD Community</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;So by now this &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/podestplatz/BCF-Plugin-FreeCAD"&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt; exists, which already houses two example BCF files in
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;examples/&lt;/tt&gt;,
supplied by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://forum.freecadweb.org/memberlist.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;amp;u=68"&gt;yorik&lt;/a&gt;. This repository is intended to be the main development repository.
I started a little UML class diagram, which you can find in
the folder &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;doc/&lt;/tt&gt; in the root directory of the repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note however, the class "Template" is just used for copy and paste. I used it to
set the font to Sourcecode Pro, which was kind of tedious, and since I didn't
know if these font changes translate to newly created classes too I have gone
with the copy&amp;amp;paste approach. The classes presented in this diagram are all for
representing the data from the markup.bcf file (except for the class "Project").
For the creation of these class diagrams I use &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dia-installer.de/download/linux.html.de"&gt;Dia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current problem I am facing is: how to represent the constraints given in
the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;extension.xsd&lt;/tt&gt; file (a link to it &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/buildingSMART/BCF-XML/tree/master/Extension%20Schemas"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). The most constraints listed in
this file are just listings of valid values for some nodes or attributes. What I
want to do is to force the user of this classes to use one of the valid values
and not have to implement extra code that checks each time the value is set or
written to a file for that matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So what possibilities do I have to choose from?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably most intuitively would be to create one enumeration class (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/enum.html"&gt;python
reference&lt;/a&gt;) for each attibute or node listed in &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;extensions.xsd&lt;/tt&gt;. The main
disadvantage her ist that these enumerations have to be maintained by hand, in
the case of a change to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;extensions.xsd&lt;/tt&gt;. That makes this first intuitive
option quite unattractive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second option that comes to mind would be to parse &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;extensions.xsd&lt;/tt&gt; and
then programmatically define the enumerations. This is possible due to the
dynamically typed nature of python. However this also implies that the classes,
containing a representation of an affected attribute or node, also have to be
modified every time the plugin starts and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;extensions.xsd&lt;/tt&gt; is parsed. This is
because the classes, of which type the class variables are, do not exist before
runtime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A third approach would also be possible where one enumeration class is written,
before runtime, with no values. Then during startup &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;extensions.xsd&lt;/tt&gt; gets
parsed and the valid values are added to the enumerations. That however has one
drawback: if the standard gets updated, and a new constraint is put upon another
field then an according class would have to be created manually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end I still have to think about how it is done best, and what is the most
maintainable version. Already I tend to latter option, because when the standard
changes, most probably also the implementation of this plugin has to change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bcf</category><category>bim</category><category>class-diagram</category><category>GSoC</category><guid>https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog/posts/how-to-represent-extensionxsd-constraints/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2019 15:54:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>BCF Reference Collection - GSoC 2019 </title><link>https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog/posts/references-to-read/</link><dc:creator>FreeCAD Community</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following is a list of all references that were mentioned in the forum. I split
them into two categories (for now): Documentation, Implementation Reference. In
former category standards and definitions are to be found (e.g.: BCF-XML
Documentation). The category "Implementation Reference" shall hold links to
examples, tutorials etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This list of references is most likely to grow over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="diskussion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Diskussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://forum.freecadweb.org/viewtopic.php?style=4&amp;amp;f=23&amp;amp;t=22641&amp;amp;start=10"&gt;Forum topic on BCF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="documentation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Documentation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/how-get-most-out-open-bim-alejandro-mata/"&gt;How to Get Most out of OpenBim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/BuildingSMART/BCF-XML/tree/master/Documentation"&gt;BCF-XML Documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://forum.freecadweb.org/viewtopic.php?f=18&amp;amp;t=12833"&gt;FEM Python coding standard&lt;/a&gt;: coding guidlines that I want to adhere to
during development (written by PrzemoF).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="implementation-reference"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Implementation Reference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/opensourceBIM/BIMbots-FreeCAD"&gt;BIMBots-FreeCAD&lt;/a&gt;: standalone plugin created by Yorik, serves as example on
plugin programming in FreeCAD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://doc.qt.io/qt-5/qtdesigner-manual.html"&gt;QTDesigner Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/teocomi"&gt;Matteo Cominetti&lt;/a&gt;: Author of the GNU BCFier plugin. May be a useful contact
on questions regarding BCF definition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/opensourceBIM/BCF-Forum"&gt;BCF Server and Forum&lt;/a&gt;: "[...] Wordpress plugin to create a 'BCF topic
server' from your wordpress installation [...]"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bcf</category><category>bim</category><category>GSoC</category><guid>https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog/posts/references-to-read/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 08:08:01 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>