<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>FreeCAD Development Blog (Posts about posts)</title><link>https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog/categories/cat_posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:info@freecadweb.org"&gt;FreeCAD Community&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 May 2019 16:05:09 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Learning XSD Syntax</title><link>https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog/posts/learning-xsd-syntax/</link><dc:creator>FreeCAD Community</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main takeaway from the XML Schema Definition Tutorial I went through today
was the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
So the node &lt;cite&gt;&amp;lt;xs:sequence&amp;gt;...&amp;lt;/xs:sequence&amp;gt;&lt;/cite&gt; is part of the definition of a
complex type, it is also called an indicator. What it does is that it tells the
XML checker that the elements specified inside have to occur in the same order
in the XML document to be valid. Also it specifies what elements may be
contained in the complex node.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This greatly improved my understanding of &lt;cite&gt;visinfo.xsd&lt;/cite&gt; which describes how a
&lt;cite&gt;viewpoint.bcfv&lt;/cite&gt; file is built. As I learned during design, the representation
of a viewpoint is almost as complex as the representation of the remaining
contents of a BCF file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought about how I coudl read the contents of a BCF into this file structure.
As my brain always does, it thinks through the whole process, from checking if
the given file is valid till the point where all the data resides in an object
in memory. This makes me prone to "reinventing the wheel" as I also design a XSD
parser/checker in my head which I then would use to check the given files before
reading them in. But a quick google search brought up a better option, namely an
offical &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://pypi.org/project/xmlschema/"&gt;python library&lt;/a&gt; for checking XML files against a schema.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least: I am pleased to announce that the first draft of the class
diagram is ready. You can find it &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/podestplatz/BCF-Plugin-FreeCAD/tree/master/doc"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if you are interested.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bcf</category><category>bim</category><category>class-diagram</category><category>GSoC</category><guid>https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog/posts/learning-xsd-syntax/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2019 04:24:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Advancing to the Viewpoint.bcf part</title><link>https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog/posts/finishing-up-the-datamodel-uml/</link><dc:creator>FreeCAD Community</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://forum.freecadweb.org/viewtopic.php?p=308095#p308095"&gt;forum post&lt;/a&gt; yesterday, Yorik pointed out that, although part of the
specification, the BimSnippet does not have to be treated with high priority. He
also referred me to Bernd and Duncan in case of questions arising.
As advised, I will consider the BimSnippet in the data model but probably won't
implement it right away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The progress I made today was mostly in understanding the BCF specification in
regards to the viewpoint.bcfv file. Multiple viewpoint files can be contained
within the folder of one topic. At the beginning of the day I thought that the
data model would be finished rather quick but as it turned out the documentation
on it is not as concise as one might wish it to be. To be more precise: the
whole section about the "Components" element is a bit confusing. It lists
multiple "properties", like &lt;cite&gt;Selection&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Visibility&lt;/cite&gt;. My intuition says that
&lt;cite&gt;Selection&lt;/cite&gt; contains a list of components that are selected, and &lt;cite&gt;Visibility&lt;/cite&gt;
specifies whether these components shall be visible or not. But in reality each
contains a list of components onto which the values of the attributes of the
respective property shall be applied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a bit confusing at first, and still is for me. Because of this ambiguity
I decided, for the further data model design, that refer to the related XML
schemas rather than the written documentation. For example here you can find the
schema for the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/buildingSMART/BCF-XML/blob/master/Schemas/visinfo.xsd"&gt;viewpoint.bcf&lt;/a&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But since the last time I have worked with XML schemas was in vocational school
(I think 2012) I have to refresh my memory on it. For that I will go through the
relevant parts of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.w3schools.com/xml/schema_intro.asp"&gt;W3CSchools: XML Schema Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;. Tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bcf</category><category>bim</category><category>class-diagram</category><category>GSoC</category><guid>https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog/posts/finishing-up-the-datamodel-uml/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2019 03:42:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Representing markup.bcf in UML</title><link>https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog/posts/representing-markupbcf-in-uml/</link><dc:creator>FreeCAD Community</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I mostly finished the UML class diagram in regard to representing the data
of the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;markup.bcf&lt;/tt&gt; file. One think I found kind of interesing while creating
the diagram is that in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/BuildingSMART/BCF-XML/tree/master/Documentation"&gt;BCF-XML-Documentation&lt;/a&gt; There is no link between a
topic and a comment, so no id of one is stored in the other. That didn't make
sense at first because I thought that one &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;markup&lt;/tt&gt; could have multiple topics,
which is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However one think what is not that obvious to me is the case with the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;BIMSnippet&lt;/tt&gt;.
On the documentation page it says that: "BimSnippet is an additional file containing
information related to one or multiple topics.". This would imply that there
would be more topics inside one &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;markup.bcf&lt;/tt&gt; file, because &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;BimSnippet&lt;/tt&gt; is,
as I understand, also just a node inside &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;markup.bcf&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding the open question from the previous post: How to represent constraints
defined in &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;extensions.xsd&lt;/tt&gt;; I thought about it a little today and came to the
conclusion that it would be the best approach to go with the last option I
listed. That means that for every node, for which constraints are listed in
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;extensions.xsd&lt;/tt&gt;, an empty enumeration/class is created which then, during
runtime, gets populated with the valid values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPDATE (2019-05-13): The inconsistency is resolved. The BimSnippet node just references one
file that does not have to be inside the topic folder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bcf</category><category>bim</category><category>class-diagram</category><category>GSoC</category><guid>https://podestplatz.github.io/FreeCAD-blog/posts/representing-markupbcf-in-uml/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2019 17:43:03 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>